Finding aid to the Margaret Brackenbury Crook Papers CA.MS.00051
Smith College Archives
Margaret Brackenbury Crook Papers
1911-1972
Smith College Archives
Crook, Margaret Brackenbury.
CA.MS.00051
1.25 linear feet (3 containers)
Professor of Religion and Biblical Literature, Minister. Collection contains biographical material, correspondence, photographs, publications, and reviews.
Biographical / Historical
Margaret Brackenbury Crook was born in Dymock, Gloucestershire, England on May 5, 1886 to Ellen Brackenbury Crook and Rev. L.G. Harris Crook. She attended St. Anne's School at Oxford, and received her BA with first class honors in 1913 from the University of London, since at that time Oxford did not grant degrees to women. Crook also earned a diploma with distinction in anthropology in 1914 from Oxon. In 1917, she received a certificate from Manchester College, Oxford, and was first in the college on completion of the three year course of study. From 1916-17, she went to France to work for the Society of Friends War Victims Relief Committee in the Marne and the Meuse.
In June of 1917 Crook was formally received into the ministry of the Unitarian and Liberal Christian Churches. In 1918 she became the minister of the Octagon Chapel in Norwich, England for two years. She was the first English woman to have entered in the training for the ministry and to have had sole charge of a large church. In 1920 Crook left England for America and became the executive secretary of the U.S. branch of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom. In 1921 she was appointed Associate Professor at Smith College, a position that she held for 33 years. In 1938, Crook became a U.S. citizen. Her primary field of research was old testament studies, and she published a variety of books, articles, and essays on the subject, including: The Literary History of the Bible (1934), The Cruel God: Job's Search for the Meaning of Suffering (1956), and Women and Religion (1964). She also edited and partially authored The Bible and its Literary Associations (1937).
In addition to her academic work, Crook was heavily involved in a variety of organizations. She was a member of the St. Anne's Society, the Society of Biblical Literature and Exegesis, the National Association of Biblical Instructors, the American Association of University Professors, served as the Smith College representative on the Corporation of the American Schools of Oriental Research, was an honorary lecturer at the Jerusalem school of Oriental research during the summer of 1934, served as president and honorary secretary of the Alumni of the American Schools of Oriental Research in 1943, 1942. She also served as president of the Women's Alliance of the Unitarian Church of Northampton and Florence Massachusetts.
Crook retired from Smith College in 1954. She never abandoned her scholastic pursuits. For 8 consecutive years she was named Sophia Smith Fellow of Smith College, an honor which was bestowed upon emeritus professors who have served the college and who continue to engage in scholarly projects. Crook lived in Northampton with her brother Waldo, who took care of her for the last few years of her life when her health began to fail. She died on May 24, 1972, after a brief illness. At the time of her death she had completed a book-long manuscript on the life and thought of the Apostle Paul.
Scope and Contents
The Margaret Brackenbury Crook Papers contain biographical materials, correspondence, photographs, publications and reviews covering Crook's career as a faculty member at Smith College.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Biographical Materials
II. Correspondence
III. Photographs
IV. Publications
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Crook, Margaret Brackenbury.; Smith College--Faculty.
- Series I: Biographical Materials
  Scope and Contents
  This section of the collection contains information on Crook's teachings and writings, her work and projects with her brother, Waldo, obituaries and memorial services.
  - Biographical Materials, 1911-1964 (Box 733.1, Folder 1)
  - Memorial Service, 1972 (Box 733.1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Correspondence
  There is one folder housing assorted correspondence dated from 1923 through 1970.
  - Correspondence, 1923-1970 (Box 733.1, Folder 3)
- Series III: Photographs
  There is one folder housing photographs of Crook from 1922 through 1959, and one undated photo.
  - Photographs, 1922-1959 (Box 733.1, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Publications
  This is the largest section of the collection, containing thirty-one folders of publications including two original transcripts and one uncorrected proof.
  - Publication: "The American Woman Graduate", 1928 (Box 733.1, Folder 5)
  - Publication: "An American Women's College", 1943 (Box 733.1, Folder 6)
  - Publication: "The Bible and its Literary Associations", 1937 (Box 733.1, Folder 7)
  - Publication: "The Book of Ruth", 1948 (Box 733.1, Folder 8)
  - Publication: The Cruel God, Job's Search for the Meaning of Suffering, 1957; 1961 (Box 733.1, Folder 9)
  - Publication: "Did Amos and Micah know Isaiah", 1954 (Box 733.1, Folder 10)
  - Publication: "The Marriageable Maiden of Proverbs 31: 10-31", 1954 (Box 733.1, Folder 11)
  - Publication: "Outline for a Course of Study for Secondary Schools Offering a Unit Bible for College Students", 1932 (Box 733.1, Folder 12)
  - Publication: "An Outline of the Literary History of the Bible", 1932 (Box 733.1, Folder 13)
  - Publication: "The Promise in Micah 5", 1951 (Box 733.1, Folder 14)
  - Publication: "Religion-A World Without Women", 1964 (Box 733.1, Folder 15)
  - Publication: "Cultural Principles in Hebrew Civilizations", 1931 (Box 733.1, Folder 17)
  - Publication: "Solomon" (song lyrics), 1952 (Box 733.1, Folder 18)
  - Publication: "Solomon" (song lyrics) Tracing Job's Story", 1962 (Box 733.1, Folder 19)
  - Publication: Assorted Song Lyrics, 1940; undated (Box 733.1, Folder 20)
  - Publication: "A Suggested Occasion for Isaiah", 1949 (Box 733.1, Folder 21)
  - Publication: The Track of the Storm, 1917 (Box 733.1, Folder 22)
  - Publication: "Women and Religious Teaching", 1926 (Box 733.1, Folder 23)
  - Publication: "Women and Religious Teaching" Women's Colleges in the United States", 1926 (Box 733.1, Folder 24)
  - Reviews and Editorials, 1961; 1963 (Box 733.1, Folder 25)
  - Publication: The Cruel God (original transcript), 1959 (Box 734)
  - Review of The Cruel God, 1959 (Box 734, Folder 1)
  - Publication: The Cruel God, 1959 (Box 734, Folder 2)
  - Publication: The Cruel God, 1959 (Box 734, Folder 3)
  - Publication: "Women in Religion" (chapters 2-7), 1963 (Box 735, Folder 1)
  - Publication: "Women in Religion" (chapters 8-12), 1963 (Box 735, Folder 2)
  - Publication: "Women in Religion" (chapters 13-15), 1963 (Box 735, Folder 3)
  - Publication: "Women in Religion" (chapters 16-19), 1963 (Box 735, Folder 4)
  - Publication: Women's Role in Religion (original transcript), 1963 (Box 735)
  - Publication: Paul and Ourselves (chapters 1-5), 1964 (Box 735, Folder 5)
  - Publication: Paul and Ourselves (chapters 6-10), 1964 (Box 735, Folder 6)
  - Publication: Paul and Ourselves, 1964 (Box 735, Folder 7)
  - Publication: Paul and Ourselves (outline), 1964 (Box 735, Folder 8)